Let me show you a video. Trigger
warning, it's of Margaret Thatcher.
Where there is doubt, may we bring
faith, and where there is despair, may
we bring hope.
>> This is Margaret Thatcher, about to
enter 10 Downing Street for the first
time as Prime Minister of the United
Kingdom in May 1979. If you can hear it
above the crowd, she's openly to quote
from the so-called prayer of Francis of
Assisi.
>> [music]
>> Thatcher opted not to mention the peace
bit, which might be for the best,
because if there was one key event which
held Thatcher's premiership in place, it
wasn't peace, but war. Here's Margaret
Thatcher on a tank.
>> [music]
>> See, Thatcher's time in office didn't
start off all that well. Her government
was really keen to cut inflation, and in
order to do so, chose to hike interest
rates to an incredible 17%.
Through all this, Thatcher's popularity
cratered. [snorts]
Immediately after delivering that poem
from Francis of Assisi, she'd boasted a
net approval rating of plus two. By the
end of 1981, the year which had involved
widespread rioting in Liverpool,
Manchester, and London, and the premiere
of the less good musical Cats, that had
dropped to minus 41. Then, something
happened which was to change ALL OF
THAT. ARGENTINIANS COME! ON THE MORNING
of the 2nd of April, 1982, 630 troops
from the Argentine military landed on
and swiftly wrested control of the
Falkland Islands. Argentina itself had
been under a military dictatorship since
1976,
and the government's campaign of
violence against its own people had led
to civil unrest. Argentina's leader,
Galtieri, thus made the decision to
seize the islands in an attempt to rally
some support behind himself and his
regime. The Argentinians hadn't expected
Britain to respond, believing the
islands to be too far away and too
unimportant to be worth defending.
Some of Thatcher's government felt
similar.
She didn't. Thatcher dispatched a task
force of 127 ships to retake the
islands. 255 British and 649
Argentine soldiers died before General
Mario Menendez surrendered on the 14th
of June. Galtieri, who had only
initiated the invasion in pursuit of
popularity, was removed from power and
the military dictatorship collapsed not
long after. Thatcher, on the other hand,
a poll carried out in June 1982 recorded
an approval rate of plus 23. A jump of
more than 50 percentage points from 18
months before. From being at risk of
being ousted by her enemies within the
Tory party, she went on to win two more
elections and become the longest-serving
Prime Minister in modern British
history. War, it seems, can sometimes be
pretty good for embattled politicians.
Whatever drawbacks it may have in terms
of casualties and cost, it can provide a
means of drumming up support where
previously it little existed.
On an unrelated note, Donald Trump keeps
threatening to invade places.